Guide to the Carleton Watkins Stereoview and Cabinet Photographs MSS.Photo 0170
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Carleton Watkins stereoview and cabinet photographs
circa 1860-1890
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Watkins, Carleton E., 1829-1916
MSS.Photo 0170
.25 Linear Feet (1 half-box)
Photographs by or published by Carleton Watkins. All but one are views of California.
Scope and Contents
Photographs by or published by Carleton E. Watkins in the form of cabinet cards or stereographs. All but one depict California scenes, including the railroad ferry Solano, Spring Valley Water Works projects in the San Francisco Bay Area, and views of Santa Monica, Monterey and Yosemite. One photograph has been identified as a work previously published by Alfred A. Hart. This collection has been assembled over a period of time and from various donors and purchases.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Various sources.
California -- Photographs; Watkins, Carleton E., 1829-1916
- Railroad ferry boat "Solano," Watkins New Cabinet Series (6 photos), after 1879
  Scope and Contents
  Description of boat on verso of cabinet cards. The ferry was built for the Central Pacific Railrioad in 1878 and went into service in 1879. The largest of its kind in the world until its sister boat the Contra Costa was built in 1914, the boat was able to carry an entire passenger train or a 48-car freight train. She was scuttled for a breakwater near Antioch in 1930.
  - 3791. C.P. Ferry Boat "Solano" crossing Straits of Carquinez (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Mrs. T. Hopkins, 1936
  - 3792. C.P. Ferry Boat "Solano" entering the Port Costa Slip (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 3794. Benicia, from Port Costa. The C.P. Ferry Boat "Solano" in her Slip (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Number handwritten on verso
  - [3798]. C.P. Ferry Boat Solano in slip at Pt. Costa waiting for train (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Unnumbered less cropped version of stereoview 3798 (also some copies of 3797).
  - 3800. C.P. Ferry Boat "Solano" discharging at Port Costa slip (Box 1, Folder 1)
    one copy gift of Mrs. T. Hopkins, 1936
    Two slightly variant croppings; one ununumbered, one less cropped version of stereoview 3800.
- Spring Valley Water Works (27 stereoviews), circa 1862-1888
  Gift of Mrs. Richmond F. Ferguson, 1977
  Construction and views of Crystal Springs and Lake Honda reservoirs and dams. All are stereoviews with yellow borders and handwritten captions and numbers. 725-730 show the construction of Lake Honda (presently known as Laguna Honda Reservoir), which was located in San Francisco's Sunset District around 7th Avenue. It was partially finished and in use in 1862. 902-924 (series is approx. 901-925) show the Crystal Springs reservoirs in the northern Santa Cruz Mountains, which were built over a period of time from about 1876 to 1891.
  - [no number or caption; possibly Lake Honda?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    No writing on stereoview, but was next to image indentified as part of Lake Honda group.
  - [725. Lake Honda] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    No text is present, but image matches annotated stereoview from the Society of California Pioneers displayed here: http://www.carletonwatkins.org/getviewbyid.php?id=1000852
  - 726. Lake Honda (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 727. Lake Honda (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 729. Little Lake Honda (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 730. Lake Honda (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 902. The Cottage (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 904. Cottage from the Dam (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 905. The Office (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 906. Waste Culvert (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 907. The Dam (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 909. The East Branch (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 910. View Down the Valley (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 911. View from the West Side of the Dam (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 912. View from the West Side of the Dam (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 913. From East Side of Dam (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 914. The Cove (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 915. The Tower (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 916. View from the Cove (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 917. The Road to the Cove (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 918. From the Road to the Cove (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 919. View from the Cove (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 920. The Upper Lake (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 921. Artesian Well (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 922. View Down the Lake (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 923. The Upper Lake (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 924. The Upper Dam (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Santa Monica pier (4 photos), 1878
  - 4504. Santa Monica Landing (Watkins Yosemite Art Gallery cabinet card) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 4505. Santa Monica Landing (Watkins New Series stereoview) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 4506. Santa Monica Hotel and Bathing Houses (Watkins New Series stereoview) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 4507. Santa Monica Railroad Wharf and Buildings (Watkins Yosemite Art Gallery cabinet card) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Watkins Pacific Coast stereoviews (4 photos)
  Purchased, 1990. Accession 1990-076.
  All four have red-orange borders and printed numbers and captions.
  - 303. Red Bluffs, looking from the West. Lower Canyon of Truckee River [photograph by Alfred A. Hart, first published as Central Pacific Railroad stereoview] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Hart, Alfred A.
  - 1084. Yowiye, or the Nevada Fall and Mt. Broderick. Yosemite Valley, Mariposa County, Cal. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2029. Wyanda, off Shubrick Point, Farallone Islands, Pacific Ocean (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2302. On the Way to the Geysers, Castle Peak (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Watkins' New Series Yo Semite and Pacific Coast cabinet cards (3 photos)
  - B 170. "As The Twig Is Bent The Tree Is Inclined." Cypress Drive. Monterey (Watkins' New Boudoir Series Yo Semite and Pacific Coast) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Related Materials
    Stanford also holds the Carleton Watkins Photographs of Carmel and the Monterey area (Calif.), c. 1882-1892 (MISC 1346): https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/6002792
  - 172. Midway Point, 18 Miles Drive, Monterey (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 444. San Miguel Church, Oldest in Santa Fe, New Mexico (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Mary Sheldon Barnes/Pacific Slope. inscribed on verso "To M.S. Barnes, Comps C.M.M. 1897"